We're making a space game and space is, well, black.
我们在制作太空游戏,太空就是黑色的
But flat black is boring.
但是这种完全的黑色太无聊了
So let's add a background to our game.
所以,让我们给游戏加上个背景
First, let's begin by deactivating our player
首先,我们先取消我们玩家对象的显示
game object, it will simply be in the way for now.
这个对我们来说太简单了(钩掉圈中的钩即可)
Next create a quad to hold our
下一步创建一个四边形来存放背景图像
background image by selecting Create - Quad
在层级视窗中点击
from the Hierarchy's Create menu.
Create - Quad
Rename this Background.
然后重命名为Background
Where is it?
这个新对象在哪?
We've created a quad, but we can't see it in our game.
我们创建了一个四边形,但是我们在游戏中看不到它
Let's switch to the Scene view to see what's going on.
我们先切换回场景视图看看发生了什么.
There it is, it's oriented in a way
在这,它旋转的角度
that's not facing the main camera.
使得它的表面并没面对相机
The main camera can't see it.
正好使得主相机看不到它
To adjust this let's first reset
我们来改变这个状况,
the game object's transform to make sure
首先我们要重置下这个对象的变形参数
it is at origin
保证它在原点
and then let's change the background's
然后让背景
transform rotation along the X axis.
沿着X轴旋转
Let's set this value to 90 degrees.
我们设定旋转90度
Now the background quad is facing
现在背景这个四边形已经面向
towards our main camera.
主相机了
and we can see it now in the game view.
现在我们在游戏视图中也能看到它
I'm going to switch back to the Scene view.
我们再切换回场景视图
The stock quad comes with a
这个存储背景的四边形
component we don't need.
自带了一些我们不需要的组建
We can safely remove the mesh collider
我们可以直接把他们去掉
component as we won't be using it.
网格碰撞检测可以去掉,因为我们不会用到它
Next, let's add a texture to this background.
下一步,我们要给背景加上材质图片
In Assets there is a directory called Textures.
在Assets文件夹中有一个目录叫Textures
Inside Textures we will find an image
Textures中有个图像文件名为
tile_nebula_green.
Let's select this image.
我们就用这个图像
When we select an image and inspect it
当我们选定并查看一个图像的时候
we are looking at that image's importer
我们看得是这个图像的导入信息
We will leave the importer settings as they are.
我们先不改变导入信息的设置
But if the preview window is open
如果预览窗口是打开的
we can some additional information about this image.
我们可以看到该图片的一些额外附加的信息
If the preview window is collapsed
如果没看到预览窗口
we can drag the bar titled Preview upwards
我们可以把预览的标题栏向上拖动
until we see the image clearly.
直到我们可以清楚的看到图像
The information at the bottom of the Preview window
预览窗口底部的信息
tells us the current resolution of the
告诉我们,当前图像的分辨率
image in our project, the current compression method,
所使用压缩格式
if any, and the total size of the imported image.
以及图像的大小
What is important for us to note here is that
这里有一点我们需要注意
this is a very large image.
当前的图像非常大
1024 by 2048.
是1024*2048的
So this image is more than large enough to stretch
所以这个图像比我们
behind our 600 by 900 game view.
600*900的游戏视野大,足够作为背景了
This is also telling us that the image is not square
同时这个信息也告诉我们
but rectangular.
这个图像不是正方形的,是长方形的
There are a number of ways that we can get
有很多种方法都可以将材质贴图
a texture on to a mesh.
贴到网格上
Let's try one of the most simply ways.
我们使用一种最简单的方法
Grab the image, drag it,
抓住图像,拖动它
and drop it on the background quad in the scene.
把它扔到场景视图的背景四边形上
Done!
完成!
Let's get a better view of our background.
让我们仔细瞧一瞧我们的背景
Use Frame Selected to focus the
我们使用框架选定来
Scene view camera
把视图相机拉近到背景对象上
The image has been applied to the background quad.
图像的确被贴到了背景四边形上
It's dark and squashed but it's there.
虽然它很暗而且压缩成了小块
What just happened?
让我回顾下刚才发生了什么
We can see that the texture has been attached
我们把材质贴到了一个材料上
to a material and the material has been
把材料与一个
associated with the quad by a reference
四边形做了关联
in the mesh renderer.
网格渲染中使用了这个被关联的四边形
Our mesh filter holds the mesh data,
我们的网格过滤器保存了网格数据
in this case the quad.
这里是存在了quad中
The mesh renderer renders that mesh using
网格渲染器使用其材料队列中的数据
the materials in the mesh renderer's Materials Array.
对网格进行渲染
The renderer is only able to use a texture
渲染器只能使用材料的材质
if it's part of a material.
进行渲染
We did not create a material, we simply
我们并没有创建新的材料
dragged the texture on to the quad.
我们只是把材质贴图拖拽到了那个四边形上
It was Unity that created the material for us.
Unity会自动创建一个材料供我们使用
When we drag a texture on to a mesh,
当我们把一个材质拖到一个网格上时
if Unity cannot find an associated material
如果Unity找不到对应这个材质的材料
with that texture Unity will create
Unity会
a new material for us.
新建一个材料
Then Unity will automatically add that material
然后Unity将自动把这个材料添加到
to that mesh renderer's Materials Array.
网格渲染器的材料队列中
This automatic material will always
这个自动添加出来的材料
with the default diffuse shader.
使用默认的散射着色器
Let's look at our background.
现在让我们再回来看背景
Is it ready to go? No.
这就算是配置好背景了么?显然不是
It's small, square, squashed,
它现在只不过是一个压缩了的小方块
a bit dark and a little hard to see.
颜色很暗很难看清楚
The first thing we need to do is scale up
首先我们得把它弄大一点
our quad to fit our background.
最好让那个四边形充满整个背景
We can do this by changing the
我们可以通过改变变形组建的
transform's Scale properties.
Scale(尺寸)属性来达到这个效果
The quad is a very simple 2 dimensional plane.
quad(四边形)是一个简单的2维平面
We can scale the quad along the X and Y axis,
我们可以改变四边形X方向和Y方向的尺寸
but not along the Z axis.
但是Z方向无效
Trying to scale the Z axis does nothing.
调整Z方向的尺寸是没有效果的
Let's reset the scale now that we've played with it.
先让我们重置下这个四边形的尺寸
What scale should we use?
我们应该用什么样的尺寸呢?
Let's first look at the texture itself.
先让我们看眼材质自己的属性
It's 1024 by 2048.
它是1024*2048的
To keep the image undistorted when we scale it up
为了让图像不失真
we should keep an aspect ratio of 1:2.
我们的长宽比应该也设定为1:2
This means our X scale should always be
这意味着X方向的尺寸始终应该是
half of our Y scale.
Y方向尺寸的一半
Or conversely our Y scale must always
或者说Y尺寸应该是
be twice our X.
X尺寸的2倍
To see this properly in the game let's
为了更清楚地查看在游戏中的效果我们先
switch back to the Game view.
切换回游戏视图
In the Game view select the background quad
在游戏视图中，选定背景四边形
and scale it along the X axis
拉大X轴方向的尺寸
until it fills the screen.
直到覆盖整个屏幕
It's more than filling the screen when we use
如果我们将尺寸值调到12
a scale value of 12 or more.
这个背景图就已经比我们的游戏显示屏幕尺寸大了
We have enough resolution that we can afford
我们的图像分辨率很高
to lose some of the image off the sides.
我们可以让图像的一些边缘显示在游戏视野之外
So let's pick a good round number,
让我们选个合适的值
like 15. It's more than big enough.
15看起来差不多,而且也够填充整个场景了
So that we can maintain our 1:2 aspect ratio
然后我们按照长宽比1:2
what is 15 times 2? 30.
15*2是30
If we have 15 in our X we need 30 in our Y.
如果我们X方向值为15,Y方向值就需要30
Now the background fills the game view
现在背景已经充满了游戏视图
with no distortion.
并且没有失真
Let's look at it in the Scene view.
让我们再切回场景视图看看
Use Frame Selected to focus the
使用框架选定来
Scene view camera to the background's new size.
看看我们背景的新尺寸
and we can see that we now have a nice big background.
现在我们有一个漂亮的大背景
The background is still a bit too dark
不过背景还是有点暗
The material is using a simple diffuse shader.
材料本身只使用了一个简单的散射着色器
This means that the texture is being treated like
这意味着,材质本人是按照
a simple painted surface using matt,
单一不光滑平面处理的
not glossy paint.
不是有光泽的平面
The surface of our background is being lit
背景是被我们场景中的光线点亮的
by the lights in our scene.
光线点亮的
These lights have been setup to light our player ship.
这些光线本来是为玩家飞船配置的
1 light, the rim light, is shining up
照射飞船的边缘光
from below and won't light the surface
是从下向上照射的,
of the background at all.
根本照不到我们的背景
The other 2 have very shallow angles
另外两个光线的角度
that only rake the surface of the quad.
决定了它们只能扫到背景的表面
So our background isn't receiving very
我们的背景并没有从
much light from our lighting rig.
我们的光系统中受到足够的照射
This is great for our player ship
整个光系统对玩家飞船来说是不错,
but not so great for our background.
但是对背景并不适用
We could add a light shining straight
我们可以增加一个光线
down to light the background.
直接照到背景上
But this would add another light to the ship
但这会给飞船也增加一个光线
lighting it in a way that we wouldn't want.
导致飞船的光照跟我们的预期不同
We could put the background and it's new light
我们可以通过将背景和新的光线
on a separate layer so that the background
配置到单独的层
light did not mix with out existing lights
这样新的光线就不会和现有的光线
on the player ship.
混合到一起了.
But there is a better way.
但是其实有一种简单的解决方法
For more information on layers and how to use them
如果想知道关于分层和如何使用分层的信息,
see the information linked below.
请查看下方连接
If we think about our background image
仔细考虑一下我们的背景图像
we simply want to have it display
我们只是要在游戏的后面
behind our game.
显示这张图而已
It's a flat plane, we do not need specialised
这个背景图就是个平面,不需要像飞船那样
lighting like we need for our ship
需要单独的光线来照射(光照产生阴影增强立体感)
and it's a waste to shine a directional light
为了点亮一个平面用方向光
on a simply quad just to flat light it's contents.
直接照在它上面上也是一种浪费
When dealing with a material,
当我们处理一个材料
how that material treats the texture
材料的材质的表现方式
depends upon what shader we choose.
取决于我们着色器的选取
Diffuse treats the texture like matte paint.
漫射将使材质看起来像一个不光泽的表面
The specular shader will treat that texture
镜面着色器将使材质
like glossy paint, or shiny plastic.
看起来很光滑,类似塑料反光那样
There are many other built-in shaders
Unity还有很多其他的内置
that come with Unity.
着色器
More can be found on the Asset Store
Asset Store(资源商城)中有更多的选择
and we can write our own custom shaders.
当然我们也可以自定义个性化的着色器
For more information on shaders
更多关于着色器信息
see the information linked below.
请参考下方连接
For our purposes we don't need any
按照我们当前的目标
specialised lighting on our background.
我们不需要单独的光线照射我们的背景
As a matter of fact we don't need any lighting at all.
事实上,我们的背景根本不需要光线
For our background, let's change the shader.
我们改一下背景的着色器
Let's choose Unlit - Texture
选择Unlit - Texture
for the shader on the nebula material.
来为我们的星运物质着色
Now our background is independent
现在我们的背景
of our lighting system, and it displays
从我们的光线系统中独立出来了
the texture exactly as it looks
材质已经跟它的原始图像
in the original image
一模一样了
and it uses no lights at all.
而且跟本没用光照
In the game it's nice and bright.
在游戏里面，这个背景看起来不错而且很明亮
If we change the shader back to diffuse
如果我们把着色器换回漫射
we can see how much darker it is in the game.
我们可以看到背景变暗了好多
Let's bring back our player and check that
我们现在把玩家飞船放回来
everything looks good in context
检查一下是不是所有的东西都正常
now that we have a background in place.
现在我们有背景了
Okay, something's wrong with our ship.
现在飞船看起来有点问题
Let's look at it in the Scene view
切回场景视图看看
to see what's going on.
到底发生了什么
Ah, the player ship is buried
啊,飞船被背景图像
in the middle of the background,
给埋起来了
they are both at origin.
它们都在原点
The background should be behind the game.
背景应该在游戏的后方
So let's grab the background and adjust it.
所以我们把背景调整一下
along the Y axis.
让它沿着Y轴后退一些
We can slide it in to a good position by hand
我们可以把背景拖拽到正常位置
or we can simply set the transform position
或者我们简单设定一下变形组建的
on the Y axis to -10.
Y轴参数为-10.
Now the background is down and out of the way.
现在背景已经调整的靠后了，不再遮挡了
When we look back at the game we can't
从游戏场景看,
see any change to the background,
貌似并没有什么变化
except for the fact that it is no longer
但飞船已经不再被
in the middle of our space ship.
埋在背景中了
This is due to the fact that our camera
这是因为我们的相机是正交的
is orthographic and has no perspective.
而不是投影的(投影模式拉远背景会造成背景变小)
The background can be any distance from the
背景与相机
camera as long as it's within it's clipping plane
任意远近的图像
and still look exactly the same.
都是一模一样的
We have now setup our background and our lighting.
我们现在设定好了背景和光
Next let's begin to create game play elements
下一步让我们增加游戏的元素
by moving the player ship.
让我们的玩家飞船动起来